<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Windows Server on Hugo&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/tags/windows-server/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Windows Server on Hugo&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Hugo Slabbert. &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;Some rights reserved&lt;/a&gt;. Please attribute properly and link back.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2009 16:24:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.slabnet.com/tags/windows-server/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>“550 4.4.7 QUEUE.Expired; message expired” when emailing mail-enabled Public folder</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/550-447-queueexpired-message-expired-when-emailing-mail-enabled-public-folder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2009 16:24:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/550-447-queueexpired-message-expired-when-emailing-mail-enabled-public-folder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working on some major upgrades to our Exchange environment over the last while. During the course of that, we started receiving NDR’s for messages sent to mail-enabled public folders. Initially, these were “MapiExceptionNotAuthorized” messages, which are related to permissions. Those were sorted out without too much trouble, as the NDR is at least somewhat descriptive. But then we started receiving a very generic NDR of &lt;code&gt;#550 4.4.7 QUEUE.Expired; message expired ##&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;not really much to go on. Exchange 2007 does give some more “in plain English, please!” information in its NDR’s, but that also wasn’t much help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;Delivery has failed to these recipients or distribution lists:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[user display name]
Microsoft Exchange has been trying to deliver this message without success
and has stopped trying. Please try sending this message again, or provide
the following diagnostic text to your system administrator.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow&amp;hellip;that was helpful&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSL Errors in Exchange 2003 Public Folder Management</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/ssl-errors-in-exchange-2003-public-folder-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 05:51:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/ssl-errors-in-exchange-2003-public-folder-management/</guid>
      <description>On a recent network audit for a prospective new client, I came across an issue in the Exchange System Manager for their Exchange Server 2003 box. When you tried to browse into any public folder management, ESM presented the following error:
The SSL certificate server name is incorrect.I checked the certificate, and it was definitely valid with a trusted Root CA. A quick web search pointed me to this Microsoft KB.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Active Directory in PHP using ADLDAP</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/accessing-active-directory-in-php-using-adldap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 05:35:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/accessing-active-directory-in-php-using-adldap/</guid>
      <description>Lately, our company has started developing user web portals for our clients. The main goal is to provide a central reference point for common links (webmail, helpdesk, remote assistance links &amp;hellip; ), howto documents, and other files and resources. A secondary goal was to also allow user administrators to perform basic user management through a web interface. This would include things like disabling/creating/unlocking user accounts, resetting passwords, and modifying group memberships for access reasons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exchange 2007: Messages stuck in Submission Queue</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-messages-stuck-in-submission-queue/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 04:32:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-messages-stuck-in-submission-queue/</guid>
      <description>We recently received reports of message delivery delays in our Exchange organization. We run Exchange 2007, so I checked out the Hub Transport Servers and discovered that messages were piling up in the Submission queues on both of the main hub transports. Restarting the Microsoft Exchange Transport service didn&amp;rsquo;t get things going again, so I turned to the Application Log to try to figure out what was going on.I noticed some errors coming from the source MSExchange Extensibility, with an event ID of 1050.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find Disabled and Inactive User and Computer Accounts using Powershell - Part II</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/find-disabled-and-inactive-user-and-computer-accounts-using-powershell-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2008 05:28:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/find-disabled-and-inactive-user-and-computer-accounts-using-powershell-part2/</guid>
      <description>Part I demonstrated how to find aged or inactive accounts, and in Part II we will look at another lingering account type: disabled accounts.
Like inactive accounts, Directory Searchers also come in handy for disabled accounts. We can also, however, read an Active Directory account&amp;rsquo;s status directly from a hidden attribute on the ADSI object. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the Directory Searcher method. This entry also draws from Bahram’s Blog. The code:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find Disabled and Inactive User and Computer Accounts using Powershell - Part I</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/find-disabled-and-inactive-user-and-computer-accounts-using-powershell-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2008 05:28:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/find-disabled-and-inactive-user-and-computer-accounts-using-powershell-part1/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ll start off with Inactive accounts first, and then work on the disabled accounts after that.
Active Directory in Server 2003 has a nice user/computer attribute called lastLogonTimeStamp that can help us keep track of inactive accounts. If you have ever tried to use that attribute, however, you might have come up with something like this&amp;hellip;
PoSH&amp;gt; $struserdn = &amp;quot;CN=Some User,OU=Users,OU=Corp,DC=yourdomain,DC=local&amp;quot; PoSH&amp;gt; $adobjuser = [ADSI]&amp;quot;LDAP://$struserdn&amp;quot; PoSH&amp;gt; $adobjuser {CN=Some User,OU=Users,OU=Corp,DC=yourdomain,DC=local}
PoSH&amp;gt; $adobjuser.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take ownership of files and folders through script</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/take-ownership-of-files-and-folders-through-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2008 04:41:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/take-ownership-of-files-and-folders-through-script/</guid>
      <description>As part of our process to disable user accounts, we take ownership of the user&amp;rsquo;s server-stored documents such as roaming profiles and redirected My Documents directories. We then either keep access restricted to the domain admins group or grant access to a replacement user who should receive access to the departed user&amp;rsquo;s files.
With an upgrade to Exchange 2007, we have taken advantage of the Powershell access to Exchange objects, and have scripted the mailbox provisioning and account disable processes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dell, Broadcom, Server 2003 SP2 SNP and TOE</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/dell-broadcom-server-2003-sp2-snp-and-toe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2008 04:03:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/dell-broadcom-server-2003-sp2-snp-and-toe/</guid>
      <description>Dell, Broadcom, and Microsoft have decided to partner up with the release of a technology called TCP/IP Offloading, or TOE for TCP/IP Offload Engine. It was bundled together in the Scalable Network Pack (SNP), included and enabled by default with Service Pack 2 (SP2) for Windows Server 2003. The gist of this technology is to enable high-load enterprise applications to be easily scalable. For those of you familiar with the OSI model, TOE moves layer 3 and 4 processing out of the OS and CPU into the NIC.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>