<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exchange 2007 on Hugo&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/tags/exchange-2007/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Exchange 2007 on Hugo&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Hugo Slabbert. &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;Some rights reserved&lt;/a&gt;. Please attribute properly and link back.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2009 16:24:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.slabnet.com/tags/exchange-2007/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>“550 4.4.7 QUEUE.Expired; message expired” when emailing mail-enabled Public folder</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/550-447-queueexpired-message-expired-when-emailing-mail-enabled-public-folder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2009 16:24:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/550-447-queueexpired-message-expired-when-emailing-mail-enabled-public-folder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working on some major upgrades to our Exchange environment over the last while. During the course of that, we started receiving NDR’s for messages sent to mail-enabled public folders. Initially, these were “MapiExceptionNotAuthorized” messages, which are related to permissions. Those were sorted out without too much trouble, as the NDR is at least somewhat descriptive. But then we started receiving a very generic NDR of &lt;code&gt;#550 4.4.7 QUEUE.Expired; message expired ##&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;not really much to go on. Exchange 2007 does give some more “in plain English, please!” information in its NDR’s, but that also wasn’t much help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;Delivery has failed to these recipients or distribution lists:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[user display name]
Microsoft Exchange has been trying to deliver this message without success
and has stopped trying. Please try sending this message again, or provide
the following diagnostic text to your system administrator.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow&amp;hellip;that was helpful&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exchange 2007: Messages stuck in Submission Queue</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-messages-stuck-in-submission-queue/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 04:32:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-messages-stuck-in-submission-queue/</guid>
      <description>We recently received reports of message delivery delays in our Exchange organization. We run Exchange 2007, so I checked out the Hub Transport Servers and discovered that messages were piling up in the Submission queues on both of the main hub transports. Restarting the Microsoft Exchange Transport service didn&amp;rsquo;t get things going again, so I turned to the Application Log to try to figure out what was going on.I noticed some errors coming from the source MSExchange Extensibility, with an event ID of 1050.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dell, Broadcom, Server 2003 SP2 SNP and TOE</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/dell-broadcom-server-2003-sp2-snp-and-toe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2008 04:03:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/dell-broadcom-server-2003-sp2-snp-and-toe/</guid>
      <description>Dell, Broadcom, and Microsoft have decided to partner up with the release of a technology called TCP/IP Offloading, or TOE for TCP/IP Offload Engine. It was bundled together in the Scalable Network Pack (SNP), included and enabled by default with Service Pack 2 (SP2) for Windows Server 2003. The gist of this technology is to enable high-load enterprise applications to be easily scalable. For those of you familiar with the OSI model, TOE moves layer 3 and 4 processing out of the OS and CPU into the NIC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exchange 2007 Mailbox GUID </title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-mailbox-guid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2008 05:46:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-mailbox-guid/</guid>
      <description>On a recent Exchange 2003 to 2007 upgrade, I ran into a very frustrating issue that significantly delayed our deployment. All new mailboxes that were created on using Exchange 2007 tools (Exchange 2007 Management Console or Powershell) were missing several crucial ADSI attributes, namely:
 legacyExchangeDN
 msExchALObjectVersion
 msExchMailboxGuid
 msExchMailboxSecurityDescriptor (set to &amp;ldquo;not set&amp;rdquo;, all other accounts have a blank value here)
 msExchUserAccountControl
  Of these, the most important seem to be msExchMailboxGuid and msExchMailboxSecurityDescriptor.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>