<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hugo&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Hugo Slabbert. &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;Some rights reserved&lt;/a&gt;. Please attribute properly and link back.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 07:17:17 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.slabnet.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What BCP38 Can and Cannot Do</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/what-bcp38-can-and-cannot-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 07:17:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/what-bcp38-can-and-cannot-do/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;re coming through what is seeming like a tipping point in the history of DDoS on the Internet. Rather than targeting a company or online gaming, one of the largest DDoS attacks ever targeted an individual, Brian Krebs, most likely for his work exposing a so-called &amp;ldquo;booter service&amp;rdquo;, a DDoS-for-hire outfit called vDOS, which ultimately led to the alleged proprietors being arrested.
A brief history of DoS volumes Public information about DDoS attack volumes are generally sparse outside of news releases and blog posts of DDoS mitigation companies, but even as late as last year, attacks of around 400 Gbps were exceptional events and pretty much the biggest the Internet had seen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clarifying DDoS-related terms</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/clarifying-ddos-related-terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2016 20:47:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/clarifying-ddos-related-terms/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ll be writing a bit more about DDoS attacks and security, and so I thought it would be handy to jot down some commonly used terms in one place. I&amp;rsquo;ll also look at how some of those terms are interrelated.
The terms Spoofing As relates to TCP/IP, &amp;ldquo;spoofing&amp;rdquo; really just refers to forging some part of IP communications. You could, for example, spoof a source port to have response data thrown at a listening application that wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting it, but generally we&amp;rsquo;re talking about forging the source IP address in an IP packet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GRE Reflection?</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/gre-reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 20:23:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/gre-reflection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, we&amp;rsquo;re seeing an uptick in GRE traffic as part of a DDoS mix.  Most prominently, GRE featured as the biggest volume contributor in the record 600+ Gbps attack on &lt;a href=&#34;http://krebsonsecurity.com&#34;&gt;krebsonsecurity.com&lt;/a&gt;.  (Note that the site is currently offline as it&amp;rsquo;s finding a new home, so any links to krebsonsecurity.com will reference &lt;a href=&#34;http://archive.org&#34;&gt;The Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; instead.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An initial tweet from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/briankrebs&#34;&gt;@briankrebs&lt;/a&gt; listed GRE in the attack traffic mix:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;per the last tweet, they threw it all at my site; SYN Flood, GET Flood, ACK Flood, POST Flood, GRE Protocol Flood]; 665.00 Gbps;143.50 Mpps&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; briankrebs (@briankrebs) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/briankrebs/status/778402188267778048&#34;&gt;September 21, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and Krebs later confirmed more details in KrebsOnSecurity&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20160922021000/http://krebsonsecurity.com/2016/09/krebsonsecurity-hit-with-record-ddos/&#34;&gt;own article&lt;/a&gt; reporting on the attack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preliminary analysis of the attack traffic suggests that perhaps the biggest chunk of the attack came in the form of traffic designed to look like it was generic routing encapsulation (GRE) data packets, a communication protocol used to establish a direct, point-to-point connection between network nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, volumetric DDoS attacks will generally use amplification vectors like open DNS resolvers, misconfigured or vulnerable NTP or SNMP servers, SSDP, etc. in order to boost the attack volume.  Those amplifiers are also often vulnerable to reflection attacks, where the attacker spoofs the source address in the initial amplification trigger packets so that the amplified replies hit the target rather than the attacker.  This can be pulled off because these exploited amplification vectors are stateless and UDP-based, and so a single spoofed packet from the attacker will trigger the amplified reply destined for the target.  A TCP-based attack could yield a larger amplification factor (e.g. just think of pulling off an HTTP GET of a GB+ file!), but a TCP 3-way handshake would never complete successfully with a spoofed source address, and even if somehow it could, the attacker would have to keep ACK-ing somehow in order to keep the transfer going.  GRE we are told, however, could not have a spoofed source address (also from &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20160922021000/http://krebsonsecurity.com/2016/09/krebsonsecurity-hit-with-record-ddos/&#34;&gt;the same Krebs article&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McKeay explained that the source of GRE traffic can’t be spoofed or faked the same way DDoS attackers can spoof DNS traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GRE is not known to have an amplification vector, and I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to think of one.  But is it true that source IPs cannot be spoofed in GRE?  *Note that this is an untested theory and still needs to be validated.*&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ubuntu Xenial and systemd network online target</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/ubuntu-xenial-and-systemd-network-online-target/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 21:42:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/ubuntu-xenial-and-systemd-network-online-target/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I&amp;rsquo;m bringing a little Chromebox back into use on our home network to do
some basic network services: dhcp, dns, and probably actually using it as a
router (long story; tl;dr TekSavvy says they&amp;rsquo;ll give you a /56 but then the
VDSL modem they sell you can&amp;rsquo;t do DHCPv6-PD properly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slapped Ubuntu 16.04 Xenial server on it and started plugging away at a
couple of things.  I opted to use ISC&amp;rsquo;s newer &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.isc.org/kea/&#34;&gt;Kea DHCP
server&lt;/a&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;isc-dhcp-server&lt;/code&gt;.  Little did I
know that Ubuntu and systemd had other ideas&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving to Hugo</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/moving-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2016 22:29:33 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/moving-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>So&amp;hellip;I&amp;rsquo;ve moved my blog to Hugo. More info to follow, but bear with me as I clean up some bits and pieces.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BTC tips</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/btc-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2016 05:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/btc-tips/</guid>
      <description>This blog hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated in a bit, but I&amp;rsquo;m experimenting with bitcoin tips. If you like an article or found it useful, please feel free to send me &amp;ldquo;thank you&amp;rdquo; tip via bitcoin through the BTC address at the bottom of the article. This is also a rudimentary &amp;ldquo;voting system&amp;rdquo; to let me know which content has been most beneficial to people.
I&amp;rsquo;ll be adding BTC tip addresses to articles in fits and starts for existing articles as I get to them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What do you run on XenServer?</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/what-do-you-run-on-xenserver/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2010 18:35:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/what-do-you-run-on-xenserver/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/XenServerArmy&#34;&gt;@XenServerArmy&lt;/a&gt; asked in &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/XenServerArmy/status/18477320394&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; what applications/services people are running on their XenServer deployments. So, here&amp;rsquo;s a quick list for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.i-worx.ca/&#34;&gt;i-worx&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Gone Google&#34; Marketing Fail...</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/gone-google-marketing-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 18:21:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/gone-google-marketing-fail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Google is touting their Google Apps offering for business with a new post on the official Google Blog (&lt;a href=&#34;http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2010/06/take-test-drive-into-cloud.html&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). The post presents a link to a gonegoogle.com site, which runs you through a calculator of how much cash you can save by &amp;ldquo;Going Google&amp;rdquo;. The calculator seems to be based on industry averages for things like uptime, storage costs, remote access, etc., and presents a nice little summary poster at the end. An example is given from guest poster smartfurniture.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice little surprise comes up, though, when you click on the link to view the sample poster for Smart Furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wordpress Theme Updated</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/wordpress-theme-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2010 05:48:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/wordpress-theme-updated/</guid>
      <description>In case it isn&amp;rsquo;t obvious: I switched up the theme for the site. I was never really too fond of the light-green touch of the previous theme and the code styling especially bugged me, but it was a fairly clean and so I just kind of stuck with it.
Anyhow; comments &amp;amp; feedback appreciated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cannot install ESET Security on Debian 4.0 Etch Virtuozzo VPS</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/cannot-install-eset-security-on-debian-40-etch-virtuozzo-vps/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2009 16:24:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/cannot-install-eset-security-on-debian-40-etch-virtuozzo-vps/</guid>
      <description>As part of some mail filter testing, I needed to install ESET Mail Security onto a Debian 4.0 Etch VPS running on Virtuozzo. As a side-note, I found that the install package for ESET’s Gateway Filter, Mail Security, and File Server Security for Linux is all the exact same package; the functionality is basically just controlled/activated by means of licensing the appropriate component.
Anyway, the download comes as an installation script called esets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“550 4.4.7 QUEUE.Expired; message expired” when emailing mail-enabled Public folder</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/550-447-queueexpired-message-expired-when-emailing-mail-enabled-public-folder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2009 16:24:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/550-447-queueexpired-message-expired-when-emailing-mail-enabled-public-folder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working on some major upgrades to our Exchange environment over the last while. During the course of that, we started receiving NDR’s for messages sent to mail-enabled public folders. Initially, these were “MapiExceptionNotAuthorized” messages, which are related to permissions. Those were sorted out without too much trouble, as the NDR is at least somewhat descriptive. But then we started receiving a very generic NDR of &lt;code&gt;#550 4.4.7 QUEUE.Expired; message expired ##&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;not really much to go on. Exchange 2007 does give some more “in plain English, please!” information in its NDR’s, but that also wasn’t much help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;Delivery has failed to these recipients or distribution lists:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[user display name]
Microsoft Exchange has been trying to deliver this message without success
and has stopped trying. Please try sending this message again, or provide
the following diagnostic text to your system administrator.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow&amp;hellip;that was helpful&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workaround for mysqldump SSL error 2026 bug #27669</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/workaround-for-mysqldump-ssl-error-2026-bug-27669/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2009 16:36:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/workaround-for-mysqldump-ssl-error-2026-bug-27669/</guid>
      <description>I had not previously played aroung much with MySQL replication, but got the chance to do so recently. I&amp;rsquo;m doing some testing with a new mail filter setup composed of amavisd-new, SpamAssassin, and some other SA modules running through Postfix on Debian Etch. The setup uses Maia Mailguard as a web front-end and management system, including per-user settings and quarantines. We&amp;rsquo;re using MySQL for the database backend for Maia for storing quarantines, per-user settings and the like, but wanted to have a dual-MX setup with a secondary MX sitting in a remote site.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Windows Media Player 11 Breaks Internet Connectivity</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/windows-media-player-11-breaks-internet-connectivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 06:18:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/windows-media-player-11-breaks-internet-connectivity/</guid>
      <description>Alright, so the title for this post seems pretty out there, but I can guarantee you that I have come across this on multiple machines. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying &amp;ldquo;If you install Windows Media Player 11 on your computer, networking will break,&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;m just saying that if you experience the symptoms outlined below and you&amp;rsquo;re stuck, trying uninstalling WM11 and the WM11 codec; you just might get lucky.
So, one of the other techs in the office calls me over: He&amp;rsquo;s been beating his head against a wall with a remote user being unable to get internet connectivity on his Windows XP workstation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSL Errors in Exchange 2003 Public Folder Management</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/ssl-errors-in-exchange-2003-public-folder-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 05:51:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/ssl-errors-in-exchange-2003-public-folder-management/</guid>
      <description>On a recent network audit for a prospective new client, I came across an issue in the Exchange System Manager for their Exchange Server 2003 box. When you tried to browse into any public folder management, ESM presented the following error:
The SSL certificate server name is incorrect.I checked the certificate, and it was definitely valid with a trusted Root CA. A quick web search pointed me to this Microsoft KB.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Active Directory in PHP using ADLDAP</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/accessing-active-directory-in-php-using-adldap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 05:35:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/accessing-active-directory-in-php-using-adldap/</guid>
      <description>Lately, our company has started developing user web portals for our clients. The main goal is to provide a central reference point for common links (webmail, helpdesk, remote assistance links &amp;hellip; ), howto documents, and other files and resources. A secondary goal was to also allow user administrators to perform basic user management through a web interface. This would include things like disabling/creating/unlocking user accounts, resetting passwords, and modifying group memberships for access reasons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exchange 2007: Messages stuck in Submission Queue</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-messages-stuck-in-submission-queue/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 04:32:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-messages-stuck-in-submission-queue/</guid>
      <description>We recently received reports of message delivery delays in our Exchange organization. We run Exchange 2007, so I checked out the Hub Transport Servers and discovered that messages were piling up in the Submission queues on both of the main hub transports. Restarting the Microsoft Exchange Transport service didn&amp;rsquo;t get things going again, so I turned to the Application Log to try to figure out what was going on.I noticed some errors coming from the source MSExchange Extensibility, with an event ID of 1050.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gmail Filesystem for Windows</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/gmail-filesystem-for-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2008 03:49:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/gmail-filesystem-for-windows/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for an easy online storage solution for Windows (and have a gmail account kicking around), check out the Gmail Drive by bjarke. It&amp;rsquo;s a free shell extension for Windows that basically adds a new drive to your computer. When you try to access the drive through Windows explorer, you are prompted for your gmail login details (you have the option of saving the details to avoid having to login each time you access the drive).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vista Offline Files and SMB Opportunistic Locks</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/vista-offline-files-and-smb-opportunistic-locks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2008 19:12:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/vista-offline-files-and-smb-opportunistic-locks/</guid>
      <description>One of our techs recently ran across a problem with a new Windows Vista Business laptop trying to synchronize offline files to a Windows Server 2000 file server. Synchronization would start, but the Sync Center in Vista would show failures for every single file that was attempted to be sync&amp;rsquo;d. The error message read something to the extent of &amp;ldquo;The process cannot access the file because it is being used by another process&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find Disabled and Inactive User and Computer Accounts using Powershell - Part II</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/find-disabled-and-inactive-user-and-computer-accounts-using-powershell-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2008 05:28:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/find-disabled-and-inactive-user-and-computer-accounts-using-powershell-part2/</guid>
      <description>Part I demonstrated how to find aged or inactive accounts, and in Part II we will look at another lingering account type: disabled accounts.
Like inactive accounts, Directory Searchers also come in handy for disabled accounts. We can also, however, read an Active Directory account&amp;rsquo;s status directly from a hidden attribute on the ADSI object. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the Directory Searcher method. This entry also draws from Bahram’s Blog. The code:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find Disabled and Inactive User and Computer Accounts using Powershell - Part I</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/find-disabled-and-inactive-user-and-computer-accounts-using-powershell-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2008 05:28:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/find-disabled-and-inactive-user-and-computer-accounts-using-powershell-part1/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ll start off with Inactive accounts first, and then work on the disabled accounts after that.
Active Directory in Server 2003 has a nice user/computer attribute called lastLogonTimeStamp that can help us keep track of inactive accounts. If you have ever tried to use that attribute, however, you might have come up with something like this&amp;hellip;
PoSH&amp;gt; $struserdn = &amp;quot;CN=Some User,OU=Users,OU=Corp,DC=yourdomain,DC=local&amp;quot; PoSH&amp;gt; $adobjuser = [ADSI]&amp;quot;LDAP://$struserdn&amp;quot; PoSH&amp;gt; $adobjuser {CN=Some User,OU=Users,OU=Corp,DC=yourdomain,DC=local}
PoSH&amp;gt; $adobjuser.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bulk Rename Files with Sequential Index</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/bulk-rename-files-with-sequential-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2008 06:31:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/bulk-rename-files-with-sequential-index/</guid>
      <description>I am pretty sure I&amp;rsquo;m not the only one who wants something more descriptive than DSC1900298.JPG to name my digital photos. And yes, I know that Windows Explorer allows you to rename pictures en masse, but I don&amp;rsquo;t like the convention they have chosen in that the first file is named [common name].JPG, then the subsequent files are named common name.JPG and so on and so forth.
I had a few requirements for how I wanted to go about this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take ownership of files and folders through script</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/take-ownership-of-files-and-folders-through-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2008 04:41:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/take-ownership-of-files-and-folders-through-script/</guid>
      <description>As part of our process to disable user accounts, we take ownership of the user&amp;rsquo;s server-stored documents such as roaming profiles and redirected My Documents directories. We then either keep access restricted to the domain admins group or grant access to a replacement user who should receive access to the departed user&amp;rsquo;s files.
With an upgrade to Exchange 2007, we have taken advantage of the Powershell access to Exchange objects, and have scripted the mailbox provisioning and account disable processes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dell, Broadcom, Server 2003 SP2 SNP and TOE</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/dell-broadcom-server-2003-sp2-snp-and-toe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2008 04:03:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/dell-broadcom-server-2003-sp2-snp-and-toe/</guid>
      <description>Dell, Broadcom, and Microsoft have decided to partner up with the release of a technology called TCP/IP Offloading, or TOE for TCP/IP Offload Engine. It was bundled together in the Scalable Network Pack (SNP), included and enabled by default with Service Pack 2 (SP2) for Windows Server 2003. The gist of this technology is to enable high-load enterprise applications to be easily scalable. For those of you familiar with the OSI model, TOE moves layer 3 and 4 processing out of the OS and CPU into the NIC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disclaimer</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/disclaimer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2008 03:03:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/disclaimer/</guid>
      <description>The information in this blog is offered AS IS with no warranties made on the content. While information relating to configuration of computer systems posted here is generally tested on my own systems, extensive testing has not been performed. I am not responsible for any loss or damages, including loss of data, that may be occur at the use of information contained within this blog.
All original content on this blog is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution License.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free PDF Printer</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/free-pdf-printer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2008 05:56:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/free-pdf-printer/</guid>
      <description>Every now and then somebody asks me if there is some way around paying Adobe hundreds and hundreds of dollars if they just want to create some PDF&amp;rsquo;s. Answer? Absolutely!
Two free PDF printers you can use are CutePDF and PDFCreator. I have not used the latter, but I use CutePDF myself, have recommended CutePDF to several people, and have not had any problems with it.
If you are looking for a bit more functionality, such as creating a single PDF from multiple PDF&amp;rsquo;s, rearranging pages or adding/removing pages, converting PDF&amp;rsquo;s to MS Office documents, etc, be sure to check out PDF Converter Pro from Nuance Software.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exchange 2007 Mailbox GUID </title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-mailbox-guid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2008 05:46:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/exchange-2007-mailbox-guid/</guid>
      <description>On a recent Exchange 2003 to 2007 upgrade, I ran into a very frustrating issue that significantly delayed our deployment. All new mailboxes that were created on using Exchange 2007 tools (Exchange 2007 Management Console or Powershell) were missing several crucial ADSI attributes, namely:
 legacyExchangeDN
 msExchALObjectVersion
 msExchMailboxGuid
 msExchMailboxSecurityDescriptor (set to &amp;ldquo;not set&amp;rdquo;, all other accounts have a blank value here)
 msExchUserAccountControl
  Of these, the most important seem to be msExchMailboxGuid and msExchMailboxSecurityDescriptor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resize VHD Files</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/resize-vhd-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2008 05:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/resize-vhd-files/</guid>
      <description>This topic has been covered a bit (here, here, and here, for instance) but I have been working on a project that utilizes Virtual Server for testing, and it came up again. A consultant that was working on the VM&amp;rsquo;s in question apparently struggled for quite some time before he asked for help on it. So, I thought I would see if another post on this might help someone out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reliable, Free P2V Solution</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/reliable-free-p2v-solution/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2008 05:48:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/reliable-free-p2v-solution/</guid>
      <description>If you have ever had to take on a Physical-to-Virtual (P2V) migration of a server or other machine, you know that you generally have a fine balance of the following triangle of factors: cost, complexity, and reliability. It seems like the only way to get an easy and reliable solution is to throw gobs of money at either a VMWare infrastructure or something like Platespin. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong: from what I&amp;rsquo;ve heard they both offer excellent solutions in that field, but it simply isn&amp;rsquo;t cheap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modifying Group Memberships with Powershell, Part II</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/modifying-group-memberships-with-powershell-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2008 23:30:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/modifying-group-memberships-with-powershell-part-2/</guid>
      <description>I had hoped to put this all in one post, but the thing would have gone on forever! Part I covered some basics in copying group memberships to an Active Directory user from another user, such as a template account, using Powershell. Part II will delve into my misadventures in gaining more control of user group memberships, including removing users from a group either by editing the group&amp;rsquo;s attributes or editing the user&amp;rsquo;s attributes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modifying Group Memberships with Powershell, Part I</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/modifying-group-memberships-with-powershell-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2008 19:03:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/modifying-group-memberships-with-powershell-part-1/</guid>
      <description>I recently had to spend hours figuring out how to properly modify Active Directory group memberships using Powershell. Some of the .Net methods have not yet been implemented, so I had to get a bit tricky with it. I could find the various bits of information I needed in various places, so I hope that collecting them here in one place is of some use to others.
The scenario was that I needed to disable user accounts in a Windows Server 2003 Active Directory environment running with Exchange 2007.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2008 18:24:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with technology since about 2006, first in systems administration and then moving onto network operations &amp;amp; engineering. Like a lot of other techies out there, I spend a lot of my time learning about new technologies out there, either for the fun of it or because I just need to make the damned thing work!
Anyway, when I come across some little tidbit of information that&amp;rsquo;s worth sharing, you&amp;rsquo;re sure to find it in here&amp;hellip;as of now of course&amp;hellip;what?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ultimate Guide to Linux Boot Problems</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/ultimate-guide-to-linux-boot-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2008 18:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/ultimate-guide-to-linux-boot-problems/</guid>
      <description>I haven&amp;rsquo;t played around much in Linux lately, but I finally dusted off my Ubuntu CD&amp;rsquo;s and started tooling around again. I already had Vista installation on my work laptop, and did not want to blow that away, so I erred on the side of caution by not letting the Xubuntu setup program install its own GRUB bootloader&amp;hellip;except then I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get into the Linux OS&amp;hellip;
So, off I go in search of GRUB install guides, and just about every how-to out there is using the basic scenario that GRUB was installed in the first place, and that it just needs to reinstall itself, which was totally not the case this time around!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update on Network Solutions Front-running</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/update-on-network-solutions-frontrunning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2008 18:37:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/update-on-network-solutions-frontrunning/</guid>
      <description>If you caught my previous post about Network Solutions&amp;rsquo; practice of domain front-running, here&amp;rsquo;s the latest bit: They are now actually claiming that this practice protects people against front-running (see CW article for more details). Their logic? Well, if the domain gets reserved when you search for it, they are preventing scammers from registering the domain and selling it back to you&amp;hellip;
&amp;hellip;uhm&amp;hellip;
Let&amp;rsquo;s try this again:
 I go to NS to search for a domain&amp;rsquo;s availability</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Solutions Domain Frontrunning</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/network-solutions-domain-frontrunning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2008 18:24:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/network-solutions-domain-frontrunning/</guid>
      <description>If you have not heard of the term cybersquatting, here&amp;rsquo;s the gist:
 Think of a domain name that someone else is likely to be interested in.
 Register/Purchase that domain.
 Wait for that person to try and register the domain for themselves.
 Sell the domain to them for a profit.
  Another spin on this idea is called domain frontrunning, where domain registrars track which domains are checked for availability (e.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>