<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>File Management on Hugo&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/tags/file-management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in File Management on Hugo&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Hugo Slabbert. &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;Some rights reserved&lt;/a&gt;. Please attribute properly and link back.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2008 03:49:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.slabnet.com/tags/file-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gmail Filesystem for Windows</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/gmail-filesystem-for-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2008 03:49:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/gmail-filesystem-for-windows/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for an easy online storage solution for Windows (and have a gmail account kicking around), check out the Gmail Drive by bjarke. It&amp;rsquo;s a free shell extension for Windows that basically adds a new drive to your computer. When you try to access the drive through Windows explorer, you are prompted for your gmail login details (you have the option of saving the details to avoid having to login each time you access the drive).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vista Offline Files and SMB Opportunistic Locks</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/vista-offline-files-and-smb-opportunistic-locks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2008 19:12:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/vista-offline-files-and-smb-opportunistic-locks/</guid>
      <description>One of our techs recently ran across a problem with a new Windows Vista Business laptop trying to synchronize offline files to a Windows Server 2000 file server. Synchronization would start, but the Sync Center in Vista would show failures for every single file that was attempted to be sync&amp;rsquo;d. The error message read something to the extent of &amp;ldquo;The process cannot access the file because it is being used by another process&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bulk Rename Files with Sequential Index</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/bulk-rename-files-with-sequential-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2008 06:31:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/bulk-rename-files-with-sequential-index/</guid>
      <description>I am pretty sure I&amp;rsquo;m not the only one who wants something more descriptive than DSC1900298.JPG to name my digital photos. And yes, I know that Windows Explorer allows you to rename pictures en masse, but I don&amp;rsquo;t like the convention they have chosen in that the first file is named [common name].JPG, then the subsequent files are named common name.JPG and so on and so forth.
I had a few requirements for how I wanted to go about this:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>