<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Groups on Hugo&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/tags/groups/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Groups on Hugo&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Hugo Slabbert. &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;Some rights reserved&lt;/a&gt;. Please attribute properly and link back.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2008 23:30:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.slabnet.com/tags/groups/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Modifying Group Memberships with Powershell, Part II</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/modifying-group-memberships-with-powershell-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2008 23:30:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/modifying-group-memberships-with-powershell-part-2/</guid>
      <description>I had hoped to put this all in one post, but the thing would have gone on forever! Part I covered some basics in copying group memberships to an Active Directory user from another user, such as a template account, using Powershell. Part II will delve into my misadventures in gaining more control of user group memberships, including removing users from a group either by editing the group&amp;rsquo;s attributes or editing the user&amp;rsquo;s attributes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modifying Group Memberships with Powershell, Part I</title>
      <link>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/modifying-group-memberships-with-powershell-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2008 19:03:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.slabnet.com/post/modifying-group-memberships-with-powershell-part-1/</guid>
      <description>I recently had to spend hours figuring out how to properly modify Active Directory group memberships using Powershell. Some of the .Net methods have not yet been implemented, so I had to get a bit tricky with it. I could find the various bits of information I needed in various places, so I hope that collecting them here in one place is of some use to others.
The scenario was that I needed to disable user accounts in a Windows Server 2003 Active Directory environment running with Exchange 2007.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>